Miscellaneous Papers in the Sigmund Freud Collection
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Miscellaneous Papers in the Sigmund Freud Collection 1866-1983 (bulk 1908-1957)
MSS84903
120 items
2 containers
.8 linear feet
9 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Writings, organizational records, biographical data, correspondence, photograph, and printed matter pertaining principally to psychoanalytic organizations and to writings by various individuals on psychoanalytic theory, the history of psychoanalysis, and the work of individual psychoanalysts. Also includes microfilm reproductions of correspondence from psychoanalysts and members of the Freud family.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Breuer, Josef, 1842-1925.; Coriat, Isador H. (Isador Henry), 1875-1943.; Federn, Paul.; Freud, Alexander, 1866-1943.; Freud, Harry, 1909-1968.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Gicklhorn, Josef, 1891-1957.; Gross, Otto, 1877-1920.; Hitschmann, Eduard, 1871-1957.; Laforgue, René.; Müller, Josine.; Oberholzer, Emil, 1883-1958.; Peller, Lili E. (Lili Esther); Pfister, Oskar, 1873-1956.
Organizations
Association des Psychanalystes de Belgique.; Deutsche Psychoanalytische Gesellschaft.; Psychological Center (Paris, France); Wiener Psychoanalytische Vereinigung.
Subjects
Psychoanalysis--Societies, etc.; Psychoanalysis.; Psychoanalysts.
Provenance
The Miscellaneous Papers in the Sigmund Freud Collection were given to the Library of Congress by the Sigmund Freud Archives between 1957 and 1988.
Access and Restrictions
The Miscellaneous Papers in the Sigmund Freud Collection are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
The papers include nine reels of microfilm made during the 1950s for the Sigmund Freud Archives. The microfilm is not available for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Scope and Content Note
The Miscellaneous Papers in the Sigmund Freud Collection span the years 1866-1983, with the bulk of material dating from 1908 to 1957. The papers are in German, English, and French and contain writings, organizational records, biographical data, correspondence, photograph, and printed matter documenting many aspects of the psychoanalytic movement. The material is organized in two series: Miscellany and Microfilm.
The Miscellany series consists primarily of material from psychoanalytic organizations and writings by various individuals on psychoanalytic theory, the history of psychoanalysis, and the work of individual psychoanalysts. Among the psychoanalytic organizations represented are the Association des Psychanalystes de Belgique, the Deutsche Psychoanalytische Gesellschaft, and the Psychological Center, a psychoanalytic training institute founded by Otto Rank in Paris in 1934. Articles on psychoanalytic theory are by Otto Gross, René Laforgue, and Oskar Pfister. The work of Josine Müller and Lili E. Peller, among others, is explored in memorials and biographical material.
The Microfilm series features reproductions of Josef Breuer’s correspondence with family and colleagues, correspondence and drafts of writings by Paul Federn, letters received by Eduard Hitschmann from Sigmund Freud, and Emil Oberholzer’s correspondence with fellow psychoanalysts. The Freud family is represented in correspondence with Alexander and Harry Freud, Sigmund Freud’s brother and nephew. Other microfilmed material includes minutes from meetings of the Wiener Psychoanalytische Vereinigung, Josef Gicklhorn’s research on Sigmund Freud, and a scrapbook assembled on Freud by Isador H. Coriat. The Sigmund Freud Archives subsequently donated originals or facsimiles of the same material to other collections of papers within the Sigmund Freud Collection. Exceptions are Emil Oberholzer’s correspondence and Isador H. Coriat’s scrapbook which exist at the Library only on microfilm.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in two series:
Miscellany, 1889-1983
Microfilm, 1866-1956
Container List
- Miscellany, 1889-1983 (Boxes 1-2)
  Writings, organizational records, biographical data, correspondence, certificates, photograph, and printed matter.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of individual or organization and thereunder chronologically.
  - American Psychiatric Association, photograph, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Association des Psychanalystes de Belgique, bulletins, 1955-1957, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Association for Child Psychoanalysis, new member lists, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Besold, F., “Bibliographia psychoanalytica Germanica, 1892-1950,” 1950-1956 (Box 1)
  - Deutsche Psychoanalytische Gesellschaft, correspondence and reports on meetings, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Dworschak, Rosa, to Rudolf Ekstein, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Ems, Fritz, certificate from a psychiatric clinic, Munich, Germany, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Gross, Otto, photocopies of articles by Gross, 1908-1920, undated (Box 1)
  - Guntrip, Harry, article on Ronald Fairbairn’s object-relations theory, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Hartel, Wilhelm Ritter von, writings and biographical data, 1889, 1908, 1929-1930, undated (Box 1)
  - Kemper, Werner, correspondence and writings on psychoanalysis in the German Third Reich and in Brazil, 1962, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Laforgue, René, “Super-Ego Individuel et Collectif,” 1954 (Box 2)
  - Müller, Josine, “Josine Müller zum Gedächtnis,” 1931 (Box 2)
  - Peller, Lili E., memorial service, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Pfister, Oskar, “Psycho-Analysis and Child Study,” 1911 (Box 2)
  - Prince, Morton, “Roosevelt as Analyzed by the New Psychology,” 1912 (Box 2)
  - Psychoanalytische Arbeitsgemeinschaft, Cologne, Germany, course listings, 1974-1984 (Box 2)
  - Psychological Center, Paris, Francis, brochures and clipping, 1934-1935 (Box 2)
  - Riemann, Henriette, “Wenn Menschen Schlafen,” 1909 (Box 2)
  - Roffenstein, Gaston, “Die Adler'sche ‘Individualpsychologie’ und die Soziologie,” 1926 (Box 2)
  - Schilder, Paul, “The Problem of Ethics,” 1940 (Box 2)
  - Storfer, A. J., Gelbe Post, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Unidentified letters, 1907, 1930 (Box 2)
- Microfilm, 1866-1956 (Reels 1-9)
  Correspondence, minutes, drafts of writings, research files, scrapbooks, and printed matter.
  Arranged by names of individuals or organizations and thereunder chronologically. Microfilm shelf no. 19,950
  - Boston Psychoanalytic Institute, Boston, Mass., scrapbook compiled by Isador H. Coriat containing clippings and reprints regarding Sigmund Freud and printed matter from psychoanalytic congresses, 1909-1940, undated (Reel 1)
  - Breuer, Josef, correspondence and printed matter, 1866-1924, undated (Reel 2)
  - Federn, Paul, correspondence and drafts of writings, 1931-1949, undated (Reel 3)
  - Freud, Alexander and Harry (Reel 4)
    - Family correspondence, 1919-1942, undated See also Reels 5-6, same heading (Reel 4)
    - Scrapbook containing printed marriage and death notices, identity cards, and clippings, 1909-1954, undated (Reel 4)
    - Family correspondence, 1930-1953, undated See also Reels 4 and 6, same heading (Reel 5)
  - Gicklhorn, Josef, research on Sigmund Freud, 1953-1954, undated (Reel 6)
  - Freud, Alexander and Harry, family correspondence, 1878-1896, 1923-1953, undated See also Reels 4-5, same heading (Reel 6)
  - Hitschmann, Eduard, letters from Sigmund and Martha Bernays Freud, 1908-1950, undated (Reel 7)
  - Oberholzer, Emil, correspondence with psychoanalysts, 1911-1956, undated (Reel 8)
  - Wiener Psychoanalytische Vereinigung, Vienna, Austria, minutes of meetings, 1906-1918 (Reel 9)